<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Love and honesty or, The modish courtier What's here to do? a pretty modish song turn'd to a ballad? in troth I think e're long, a fourth part of the town will poets be, if that a line of wit they can but see: they must be medling and add further still, and never leave till all that's sence they kill: yet if I iudge aright, the vulgar sort are mightily beholding to them for't. The Duke of Monmouth's jigg. With allowance, Ro. L'Estrange. Feb. 8. 1676.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B26257</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827830</idno>
  <idno type="VID">198014</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240857643</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3197</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827830</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99827830e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B26257)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 198014)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 21232:96-97)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Love and honesty or, The modish courtier What's here to do? a pretty modish song turn'd to a ballad? in troth I think e're long, a fourth part of the town will poets be, if that a line of wit they can but see: they must be medling and add further still, and never leave till all that's sence they kill: yet if I iudge aright, the vulgar sort are mightily beholding to them for't. The Duke of Monmouth's jigg. With allowance, Ro. L'Estrange. Feb. 8. 1676.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E. Oliver, at the Golden-Key, on Snow-hill, over-a-gainst St. Sepulchres-Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1676]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse - "A curse on the zealous and ignorant crew,".</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:198014:1"/>
            <head>Love and Honesty <hi>OR,</hi> The Modish Courtier.</head>
            <argument>
               <q>
                  <l>What's here to do? a pretty Modish song</l>
                  <l>Turn'd to a Ballad? in troth I think e're long,</l>
                  <l>A fourth part of the Town will Poets be,</l>
                  <l>If that a line of Wit they can but see:</l>
                  <l>They must be medling and add further still,</l>
                  <l>And never leave till all that's sence they kill:</l>
                  <l>Yet if I Iudge aright, the vulgar sort</l>
                  <l>Are mightily beholding to them for't.</l>
               </q>
            </argument>
            <opener>
               <hi>To a pleasant new Tune, called,</hi> The Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Jigg. <hi>With Allowance, Ro. L'Estrange.</hi>
               <date>
                  <hi>Feb.</hi> 8. 1676.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>two men, one offering someting (a chalice?) to the other</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>a man</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> Curse on the zealous and ignorant crew,</l>
               <l>Who languish all day,</l>
               <l>And with passion obey,</l>
               <l>The senceless decrees that Platonicks pursue.</l>
               <l>How poor and unhappy;</l>
               <l>Vnhappy are those pretenders,</l>
               <l>Who fearful of scandal and vulgarly shame,</l>
               <l>Diminish their flame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But blest be the man who with freedom enjoys,</l>
               <l>A Beauty whose Eyes,</l>
               <l>Like the Stars in the Sky,</l>
               <l>Procures new delight till his appetite cloyes.</l>
               <l>How happy unhappy,</l>
               <l>How happy are those pretenders,</l>
               <l>Who fearless of scandal or vulgar reproach,</l>
               <l>Pursue their debauch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elizium's</hi> a grief and a torment, compar'd</l>
               <l>To those that can prove,</l>
               <l>The enjoyment of Love,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>re Lovers in raptures do meet a reward.</l>
               <l>The tales of the antients,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Elizian</hi> fields are ungrounded,</l>
               <l>In Loves kind fruition where souls have access,</l>
               <l>Oh there's the true bliss.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Those conquering beauties more pleasure afford,</l>
               <l>To such as are free,</l>
               <l>At their own liberty,</l>
               <l>Then Vsurers Chests which with plenty are stor'd.</l>
               <l>Then happy be still,</l>
               <l>Noble Lads that are natures adorers,</l>
               <l>Whilst envy and avarice starve and repine,</l>
               <l>We'l frolique in Wine.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of a man surrounded by flowers</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of a woman surrounded by flowers</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:198014:1"/>
               <l>Those that the confinement of Wedlock refuse,</l>
               <l>May live at their ease,</l>
               <l>And enjoy when they please,</l>
               <l>Being free from the strict matrimonial noose.</l>
               <l>The bawling of brats,</l>
               <l>Shall not injure his rest nor his quiet,</l>
               <l>But when with delights his fierce appetite's cloy'd,</l>
               <l>Then rest is enjoy'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No wonder why clowns who of sence are debar'd,</l>
               <l>Remain till they dye,</l>
               <l>Like a Hog in a Stye,</l>
               <l>And ne'r understand a brisk Lovers reward.</l>
               <l>'Tis those that have souls,</l>
               <l>Of the modish new slamp that are witty,</l>
               <l>All others are drudges and never are blest,</l>
               <l>Till death gives them rest.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Tis Love that does give us true sence of our life,</l>
               <l>And makes us proceeed,</l>
               <l>In each generous deed,</l>
               <l>Protected with love, or are freed from all strife.</l>
               <l>But those that ne'r knew,</l>
               <l>The delights of an amorous Lover.</l>
               <l>Can't truly be said to have liv'd out an hour,</l>
               <l>If free'd from Loves power.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Those that for abundance do match with a wife,</l>
               <l>Are troubled with an itch,</l>
               <l>To be wealthy and rich,</l>
               <l>Which keeps them in torment all days of their life.</l>
               <l>They never enjoy,</l>
               <l>But still grumble at every misfortune,</l>
               <l>Whilst wisdom creates in a generous mind,</l>
               <l>Ioys they cannot find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>God Cupid for ever thy name I'le adore,</l>
               <l>For now I can see,</l>
               <l>That in thy Deity,</l>
               <l>Are blessings (for those that deserve them) in store.</l>
               <l>A passion that's noble,</l>
               <l>Shall ever receive satisfaction,</l>
               <l>But ignorant fools who abandon thy name,</l>
               <l>Extinguish their flame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In liberty all men have cause to rejoyce,</l>
               <l>If mingled with Love,</l>
               <l>Ever happy 'twill prove,</l>
               <l>What fops do count folly, we think our best choice.</l>
               <l>A cup of the creature,</l>
               <l>Will make our bloods warmer and warmer,</l>
               <l>Like senceless Fanaticks we'l never repine,</l>
               <l>Of Love and good Wine.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for <hi>E. Oliver,</hi> at the <hi>Golden-Key,</hi> on <hi>Snow-hill,</hi> over-a-gainst St. <hi>Sepulchres-Church.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>